Okay so today's דף daf is כח. chaf chet. One quick sentence
about yesterday's דף, daf, which is it was quite fascinating to note
that in the middle of all the discussions about the regular שמונה
עשרה Shmoneh Esrei we introduce this משנה Mishnah about a private תפילה
Tefillah that רב נחוניא בן הקנה Rav Nechunya ben HaKana would say
when he would go into the בית מדרש. Beit Midrash. Actually some
places they still sell stickers to put inside of your גמרות Gemaras
or whatever to actually have that תפילה. Tefillah. But right in the
middle of saying the you know the hours and the times that
you דאוון, daven, in the next משנה Mishnah that says about the
18 ברכות, brachot, we have this private שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei which
I think excuse me this private תפילה. Tefillah. Which I think again
raises for us this question about the sort of statutory prayer and
the sense of personal prayer and thinking about how those two things
have to find a way to coexist that we sort of this
because that משנה Mishnah was really seemingly out of place. The other
thing I'll also just mention and then we'll begin is that the
different sort of symbolisms of the 18. You know you wonder why
the גמרא Gemara has to find a symbolism for 18 and we're
going to go back to that you know maybe it's just that
that was all we had to say.
But somehow it feels that if you're going to pick a number
there's going to be some symbolism. Anyway the different things that the
גמרא Gemara says: one based on the הבו להשם בני אלים, Havu
l’Hashem benei elim, a פרק perek in תהלים Tehillim that is about
praising God; one about the names of God in the שמע; Shema;
one about the vertebrae in the spine, which I understand is not
accurate based on the emails that were being exchanged. But anyway all
those also seem to suggest different models about how we're thinking about
primary תפילה Tefillah and what שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei is about. You
know is it primarily about sort of praising God, which is admittedly
not the core שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, but do we primarily when
we think about תפילה Tefillah think about praising God, הבו להשם בני
אלים, Havu l’Hashem benei elim, הבו להשם כבוד ועוז? Havu l’Hashem kavod
v’oz? Do we think about it as some more of a sort
of like שמע, Shema, which is number one sort of an attestation
of faith and it's also a way in which we sort of
reaffirm for ourselves our relationship to God? So it's less our giving
praise to God as sort of underscoring and affirming our connection to
God is how I would understand the שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei connection.
Or the bending down, which is how we more understand the שמונה
עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, the supplication and submission and so on. So I
think it's interesting just there the things that it might be suggesting
different models of what we think תפילה Tefillah is. And with that
we continue now at the bottom of כח עמוד ב, chaf chet
amud bet, two lines from the bottom. תנו
רבנן: Tanu rabbanan: שמעון הפקולי Shimon HaPakuli הסדיר hisdir שמונה עשרה shmoneh
esrei ברכות brachot לפני רבן גמליאל lifnei Rabban Gamliel על הסדר al
haseder ביבנה. b’Yavne. So famous גמרא, Gemara, the academics go to town
about this about exactly understanding when the שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei was
composed and organized. שמעון הפקולי Shimon HaPakuli organized, didn't compose. Presumably these
ברכות brachot were already present and we do have evidence by the
way that even you know that even at a time of the
תנאים Tannaim they were not that the entire ברכות brachot were fully
the texts were fully fixed, that there was a certain amount of
latitude. There was like a structure and it was clear what the
end ברכה bracha was, but there was a certain amount of latitude
and maybe even some places you could even combine certain ברכות, brachot,
there might have even been a certain latitude even in some of
the structure. So anyway it's not like they're saying that he was
the author. But nevertheless שמעון הפקולי Shimon HaPakuli somehow organized the 18
ברכות brachot in front of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel על הסדר al
haseder in the court order that we have them in in יבנה.
Yavne. אמר להם רבן גמליאל לחכמים: Amar lahem Rabban Gamliel l'chachamim: כלום
יש אדם שיודע לתקן ברכת הצדוקים? Klum yesh adam sheyodeia l'taken birkat
ha-Tzaddukim?
Is there anybody here that knows how to establish the ברכה bracha
of the הצדוקים? ha-Tzaddukim? Now our גרסה girsah is הצדוקים, ha-Tzaddukim, I
didn't check, but I'm probably positive it's מינים. Minim. Right, ברכת המינים
Birkat HaMinim is what it is, the ברכה bracha of the מינים,
Minim, of the heretics, the apostates. And as I've told you many
times, מינים Minim in the גמרא Gemara almost always means the Jewish
Christians. So it's not just any apostate, it really means the מינים
Minim which were the biggest sort of threat or seen as the
potential breakaway and as we know they did break away and become
a separate religion. But anyway it was the Jewish Christians. So does
somebody here know how to establish that
ברכה? bracha? So עמד שמואל הקטן ותקנה. amad Shmuel HaKatan v'tiknah. שמואל
הקטן Shmuel HaKatan got up, stood up and he was the one
that established it, that wrote it presumably. So
לשנה אחרת l'shanah acheret and the next year שכחה. shachachah. He forgot
it, presumably as we're going to see, it was maybe even in
the middle of דאוון davening שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei and being a
שליח ציבור shliach tzibur he forgot it.
So okay והשקיף בה שתים ושלוש שעות v'hishkif bah shtayim v'shalosh sha'ot
and he was sort of looking into it, thinking about it, you
know trying to remember it for two or three hours, ולא העלוהו,
v'lo heeluhu, and he was not and even though he could not
remember it, they did not remove him from his post as the
שליח ציבור. shliach tzibur. So גמרא Gemara says אמאי? amai? Wondering if
they were all sitting around waiting two or three hours for him
to finish
שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. But anyway אמאי? amai? Why did they not
remove him from his post? ואמר רב יהודה אמר רב: Ve-amar Rav
Yehuda amar Rav: טעה בכל הברכות כולן אין מעלין אותו. Ta'ah b'chol
ha-brachot kulan ein ma'alin oto. If somebody forgot any of the ברכות
brachot in the middle of שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, a שליח ציבור,
shliach tzibur, you do not basically remove him. ובברכת הצדוקים... u'v'virkat ha-Tzaddukim...
I mean not forgot, made an error... if he makes an error
in the ברכה, bracha, ברכת המינים, Birkat HaMinim, of the ברכת המינים,
Birkat HaMinim, מעלין אותו. ma'alin oto. You do remove him. חיישינן שמא
מין הוא. Chashinan shema min hu. You're afraid that the reason he's
having a problem making this ברכה bracha is
he himself is a מין. min. Which by the way shows this
concern of course that you know that... There are these people are
among us and we have to find out who are these people
among us that are the very sort of pernicious presence. That's the
concern of מינים minim is that they basically from us but they
have a bit of a heretical type of a position, so it's
pernicious and we have to be very concerned who they might be.
So therefore somebody is not, is stumbling over this ברכה, bracha, we
get rid of them as a שליח ציבור. shliach tzibur. Now I
should make a mention: why did it say מעלין? ma'alin? מעלין ma'alin
seems to be a good thing, right? You give them an עליה,
aliyah, you raise them up. So exactly, because as we learned before,
you דאוון daven from a deep place, you דאוון daven from a
low place, so you're raised לפני התיבה lifnei hateiva when you go
to be the שליח ציבור, shliach tzibur, you go down. So if
you're being removed, you're being מעלים, ma'alim, you're bringing them back up.
So it's interesting that that's the verb used. Anyway, even while he's
still דאוונינג. davening. Yes, no, no, while he's presumably while he's still
דאוונינג. davening. Oh my God, you might be a מין, min, get
out of here, we're bringing, put someone else in there. Right. So
like we're going to have that later, הטועה בשמע שמע מחזירין אותו,
hato'eh b'shma shma machzirin oso,
we'll see those types of things where they were concerned who their
שליח ציבור shliach tzibur was. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says if
you're not
a Zionist, you don't say this particular...
Right,
there you go. So it says, חיישינן שמא מין הוא, chaishinan shema
min hu, so the גמרא Gemara says,
here finally it has the phrase שמא מין הוא, shema min hu,
interesting that one it didn't, we don't have self-censored. So the גמרא
Gemara says: why don't we do it for שמואל הקטן? Shmuel HaKatan?
It says: no, שאני שמואל הקטן דאיהו תקנה, shani Shmuel HaKatan d'ihu
tiknah,
he is the one that originally established it. We're not concerned that
he himself
was the closet heretic, although sometimes that's דווקא davka the way things
work out. So the גמרא Gemara says: וניחוש שמא הדר ביה? venechosh
shema hadar bei?
Maybe he did, maybe he reverted his position. Maybe he started being
really against them and then he got intrigued by them and then
went over to the other side. So the גמרא Gemara says: אמר
אביי, amar Abaye, גמירי דטבא לא הוי בישא, gmiri d'tava lo havi
bisha,
we have a tradition, דטבא לא הוי בישא. d'tava lo havi bisha.
If you're good, you don't become bad. That's interesting. ולא? v'lo? Is
that really not the case? והכתיב, v'haksiv, the פסוק pasuk says ובשוב
צדיק מצדקתו ועשה עול. u'vshuv tzadik mitzidkaso v'asah avel.
When a righteous person goes back from his righteousness
and does iniquity. So you see that a person who's righteous could
become a sinner. So the גמרא Gemara says: לא, התם רשע מעיקרא.
lo, hatam rasha mei'ikara. That was a guy that originally was a
רשע, rasha, then became a צדיק, tzadik, then he can backslide. But
צדיק מעיקרא לא. tzadik mei'ikara lo.
But somebody who's always been righteous, he won't turn back. ולא? v'lo?
Is that not, will that not happen? והתנן, v'hatnan, אל תאמין בעצמך
עד יום מותך. al ta'amin b'atzmecha ad yom mosecha.
Do not believe in yourself until the day of your death, שהרי
יוחנן כהן גדול שימש בכהונה גדולה שמונים שנה ולבסוף נעשה צדוקי. sheharei
Yochanan Kohen Gadol shimash b'khuna gedola shmonim shana u'levasof na'aseh Tzaduki. יוחנן
Yochanan who was a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, שימש בכהונה גדולה שמונים
שנה, shimash b'khuna gedola shmonim shana, was a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
for eighty years, ולבסוף נעשה צדוקי, u'levasof na'aseh Tzaduki,
and at the end he became a צדוקי. Tzaduki. This is probably
צדוקי Tzaduki because that was the whole problem was that the כהנים
kohanim were dominant in the as the כהנים. kohanim. So here you
see... yeah, and there
and there, and we clearly have evidence about חז''ל Chazal being afraid
that the כהנים kohanim and the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol on יום
כיפור Yom Kippur or whatever would be following the rulings of the
צדוקים. Tzadukim. We know from Josephus and elsewhere that the כהנים kohanim
were the צדוקים, Tzadukim, were very dominant amongst the כהנים. kohanim. But
they were Jewish, right? They were Jewish. So was the מין. min.
I said, Hebrew Christians, so were the מין. min. They were Jewish,
they just
had heretical beliefs.
But what was the heretical belief of the צדוקים? Tzadukim?
I don't know, we would call,
they basically... depends on what phrase you use. Heretical, I was using
as a catchall. They basically
rejected the rabbinic תורה שבעל פה, Torah she'be'al peh, the rabbinic traditions
about תורה. Torah. They had the... they basically accepted תורה שבכתב. Torah
she'biktav. They had their own explanations about how to read all the
פסוקים psukim and so... what? צדוקים, Tzadukim, not the מינים. minim. But
the מינים minim were the followers of Jesus. But some תורה...
Torah... I'd say it's the same as...
yeah well קראים Karaites were their reincarnation about a thousand years later.
They didn't accept the authority of the rabbis.
Right, right, correct. But they were from more the, they were more
the upper class. The rabbis were more from like the middle class,
number one, and they were just interesting as a class difference. And
they were, they were the, primarily the כהנים kohanim were the צדוקים,
Tzadukim, the rabbis were the rabbis, and they had their own, they
did not accept the rabbinic reading, understanding, readings of the פסוקים. psukim.
Now what about the אסיים? Essenes?
That's different, yeah, that doesn't get discussed, yeah, but that doesn't get
discussed in the גמרא. Gemara. I mean we know that from Josephus.
Right. Let's, let's, we can't do a whole thing about the various
sects, but yes.
Yeah, the New Testament says
that they didn't believe in angels and they didn't believe in life
after death.
Okay, there you go, the צדוקים. Tzadukim. Okay. All right, so now
the גמרא Gemara continues.
Yes, if we're kind of juxtaposing these because it occurred to me
that we have control or the people who are discussing this have
control over who's the שליח ציבור, shliach tzibur, but apparently not over
who's the כהן kohen or who's the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol.
Well, yes, because if the כהן, kohen, if the כהנים kohanim are
the ones that are running the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and they're
the צדוקים, Tzadukim, then...
exactly. Right. Now I should say that the questions, so clearly right,
if the כהנים kohanim were sort of controlling and also the, you
know... the other
גמרות Gemaros about how the Roman authorities had control over who is
the כהן גדול kohen gadol because they really were the sort of
religious representative of the people and the Romans were invested in that
as well. So yes, the rabbis were not able to control who
was the כהן גדול kohen gadol but could they control what was
going on in the שול shul is also a bit of a
question because it's, you know, it seems clear from the archaeological evidence
that the leadership of the שול shul was not the, was not
the rabbis. There was an independent leadership of the שול. shul. The
rabbi, you know, a lot of time we find rabbis seem more
like visitors to the שול shul or that they seem more like
they're דאוונינג davening in their own בית מדרש. beis medrash. So there
does seem to have been independent, not necessarily in opposition with the
rabbis, but still more of a lay leadership or an independent leadership
of the שול. shul. So it's not clear here that through who
is removing them, but yeah, they certainly had I would say more
sway in the שולס shuls than they did in the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
ah, so how could he have done this?
So right, don't we see that a צדיק tzadik can become a
רשע? rasha? Chronological problem. Yeah, right, שמואל הקטן Shmuel Hakatan
was a תנא Tanna or he existed in the time
of
and they're saying how could they not have removed him because we
have a statement of רב. Rav.
Right. Okay, but we actually have a פסוק. pasuk. I mean, ומשוב
צדיק מצדקתו. U’mishuv tzadik mitzidkato. Oh you mean
רב Rav that about, yeah, that's a good point. We're always doing
that. That's a good point, that the idea about, about assuming that
פסוקים psukim we say later should have been in force earlier. That's
an excellent point. Yeah, that is correct. That is correct. אמר אביי,
Amar Abaye, that's correct. So אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, הוא ינאי הוא
יוחנן. Hu Yannai Hu Yochanan. No, that יוחנן Yochanan was also, he
started as a רשע, rasha, he started as ינאי. Yannai. We know
all those terrible stories about ינאי Yannai and killing off the sages
and so on. So he also originally was a רשע rasha and
that's how he could have backslid and become a רשע rasha again.
רבא אמר ינאי לחוד ויוחנן לחוד. Rava amar Yannai lachud v'Yochanan lachud.
No, they were different personalities. ינאי רשע מעיקרא ויוחנן צדיק מעיקרא. Yannai
rasha me'ikara v'Yochanan tzadik me'ikara. ינאי Yannai started off as a רשע,
rasha, יוחנן Yochanan started off as a צדיק tzadik and יוחנן Yochanan
therefore, this יוחנן, Yochanan, eighty years he was a כהן גדול, kohen
gadol, he was a צדיק tzadik and in the end he became
a רשע. rasha. So now the גמרא Gemara says הניחא לאביי. Hani’cha
l’Abaye. So according to אביי Abaye we can accept, it's so funny
like this is the totality of our understanding of, you know, human
nature. So according to אביי, Abaye, we understand that anybody who became
a רשע rasha started as a רשע. rasha. אלא לרבא קשיא. Ela
l’Rava kashya.
According to רבא Rava he says you could have been a צדיק
tzadik your whole life and become a רשע. rasha. So how could
they not have removed שמואל הקטן Shmuel Hakatan if he was stumbling
presumably we should be suspicious that he was a צדוקי, Tzeduki, I
mean he was a מין, min, excuse me. So אמר לך רבא,
צדיק מעיקרא נמי דמרד בה. Amar lach Rava tzadik me'ikara nami d'marda
beh. No, you know what,
אמר לך רבא Amar lach Rava, צדיק מעיקרא נמי דמרד בה. Tzadik
me'ikara nami d'marda beh. So I jumped ahead to the question. So
רבא Rava says you're right, I don't think only a רשע rasha
can become a, somebody who started as a רשע rasha can backslide,
even somebody that's always been a צדיק tzadik could backslide and could
backslide, could go, could abandon his path and become a רשע. rasha.
אי הכי אמאי לא סלקוהו? Ei hachi amai lo silku'uhu? Why did
they not remove שמואל הקטן Shmuel Hakatan if he was stumbling over
ברכת המינים? Birkas Haminim? שאני שמואל הקטן דאתחיל בה. Shani Shmuel Hakatan
d'atchil beh.
No, that was different. He started doing the ברכה bracha correctly and
then he started stumbling. And somehow if you start doing the ברכה
bracha it shows that you're prepared to say it and we're not
going to be suspicious. דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Damar Rav Yehuda
amar Rav,
again anachronistically we quote a statement from, from later because רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda says the same רב יהודה אמר רב Rav Yehuda amar
Rav that said that if you stumble over ברכת המינים Birkas Haminim
we remove you, he says, דתימא רבי יהושע בן לוי לא שנו
אלא שלא התחיל בה אבל התחיל בה גומרה. D'teima Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi lo shanu ela shelo hitchil bah aval hitchil bah gomrah. That's
only if you didn't start saying the ברכה bracha but once you
started saying it, then גומרה, gomrah, then you finish it. So now
how do you finish it if you don't know it? I don't
know, but anyway you finish saying the שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. So
we only remove you if you basically are skipping the ברכה bracha
completely, but if once you started the ברכה bracha we're not concerned.
Again once somebody knows the rules of course, you know they can
play the game, but okay. Anyway somehow this is a theme we're
going to see later about people that are not or misstating or
not saying certain parts of the דאוונינג, davening, a concern that they
might be like, you know, this wolf in sheep's clothing that they
might not be what they appear to be and a concern about
removing them, which is quite fascinating, you know, also about, sort of
about how seriously they took the דאוונינג, davening, you know, that if
there was something that rather than sort of go about if you're
being a closet מין, min, rather than you know you would be
more prepared to not say the thing and to give up your,
you know, your identity than you would be to say something you
didn't believe in. So it's interesting, you know, I think this statement
about what you say in your prayer is a really profound statement
about your, your religious identity. I think that's certainly, you know, significant
right there. Again the difference between if you stumble at the beginning
or you stumble in the middle, you know, it's not so clear
to me but somehow the assumption that once you begin saying it,
it's clear that you essentially say you buy into it. Now it
is worth noting that this שמואל הקטן Shmuel Hakatan who said this
ברכת המינים, Birkas Haminim, he is known for saying what? Does anybody
know what he says in פרקי אבות? Pirkei Avos? He actually his
statement in פרקי אבות Pirkei Avos is really a פסוק, pasuk, it's
not even his own statement. שמואל הקטן אומר בנפול איביך אל תשמח.
Shmuel Hakatan omer binpol oyvecha al tismach. So you know with the,
so some want to say that because basically you know that חז"ל
Chazal felt this need to make this
ברכה bracha against... too sort of militant and too aggressive and takes
joy in saying, in attacking people that are against him. So some
want to connect the idea that the same שמואל הקטן Shmuel HaKatan
who says בנפול אויבך אל תשמח Binfal Oyivecha Al Tismach is the
one that they have to say the ברכת המינים. Birkat HaMinim. Now
again it is interesting the question what התקין hitkin mean and התקין,
hitkin, does it mean it wasn't in place at all beforehand? On
the other interesting thing is and there's a whole article I could
try to see if I could get and post for you about
the different texts of ברכת המינים. Birkat HaMinim. There really seem to
be very sort of divergent traditions around it not just because obviously
they would have gone through periods of censorship, self-censorship, because or changed
because of the historical context, but also that there really does seem
to be different beyond those sort of censorship issues or self-censorship,
different degrees to which it's a short ברכה beracha or long ברכה.
beracha. The other thing I should say is that we don't have
18 ברכות berachot in שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, we have 19, and
the גמרא Gemara itself mentioned yesterday and the general assumption is that
the 19th was this ברכת המינים Birkat HaMinim because it, here we
talk about it as a special thing presumably something that was added
later, it was added in יבנה. Yavneh. The earlier שמונה עשרה Shemoneh
Esrei was maybe אנשי כנסת הגדולה. Anshei Kinesset HaGedolah. So there's an
assumption that ברכת המינים Birkat HaMinim was the 19th although that is
not universally agreed upon. Some say that actually it has to do
more with בונה ירושלים Boneh Yerushalayim and מצמיח קרן ישועה Matzmiach Keren
Yeshuah which are very similar ברכות berachot and in some texts we
find them as one ברכה beracha that maybe they were one and
they were later then separated into two. So there is a question
of
exactly how it finally coalesced and what became the 19th ברכה. beracha.
Okay. Now that we have that type of overview about the 18-19
ברכות, berachot, we're going to talk about the other numbers that we
have for שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei again assuming that the numbers are
not just arbitrary but actually somewhat chosen because they're somewhat symbolic. So
let's take a look at דף כ״ט. Daf Chaf-Tet. Yeah. Alright. So
גמרא Gemara says now. הני שבע דשבתא כנגד מי? Hani Sheva DeShabata
Kineged Mi? The seven ברכות berachot of שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei of
שבת, Shabbat, what are they, what do they represent? Now that would
seem like an easy, that's of course a softball question. Okay, but
interestingly the גמרא Gemara does not give the obvious answer. Why do
we have seven ברכות berachot on שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei on שבת?
Shabbat? So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב חלפתא בן שאול כנגד
שבעה קולות שאמר דוד על המים. Amar Rav Chalafta Ben Shaul Kineged
Shivah Kolot SheAmar David Al HaMayim. The seven times it says קול
ה׳ על המים, Kol Hashem Al HaMayim, קול ה׳ Kol Hashem here
in like what we see the פסוק pasuk in the פרק perek
of תהילים Tehillim that we say in קבלת שבת. Kabbalat Shabbat. So
it says קול ה׳ Kol Hashem so it says קול kol seven
times, that's כנגד keneged שבת. Shabbat. I have to tell you I
don't begin to understand the answer. Like why do we assume that,
I know now it's in our קבלת שבת, Kabbalat Shabbat, but קבלת
שבת Kabbalat Shabbat was
written much much later, 16th century, why do we now assume that
that פרק perek in תהילים Tehillim is connected to שבת? Shabbat? And
why don't we say the obvious thing? Seven ברכות berachot of שבת
Shabbat because it's the seventh day of the, because of seventh day
of the week. So I don't understand that at all.
That's an excellent question because really it's three plus three plus one.
It's really just one ברכה beracha of שבת. Shabbat. I mean right
you could even have to ascribe similar
questions to
גמרא Gemara also has to right exactly.
But even if you're ascribing symbolism why focus on that פרק perek
of תהילים? Tehillim? I really don't know. So now it goes on.
I think it's because the תורה Torah was given on שבת. Shabbat.
What? Okay.
Because the number of the ברכות berachot in the שבת Shabbat corresponds
to the seven voices
mentioned at מתן תורה. Mattan Torah.
Yeah but that's this פרק perek of תהילים Tehillim is not מתן
תורה. Mattan Torah. But okay. Anyway so it's a very roundabout way
of giving something which could have been a very straightforward answer. So
anyway.
Okay. הני תשע דרש השנה כנגד מי? Hani Tesha DeRosh Hashanah Kineged
Mi? Now why do we have nine of ראש השנה? Rosh Hashanah?
So there too you could say like Dov was saying that's also
an easier answer not that nine is symbolic but you have the
three opening and the three closing and מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות Malchuyot Zichronot
VeShofrot which חז״ל Chazal learn from other places, and clearly they had
this understanding of מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות Malchuyot Zichronot VeShofrot so you plop
it into שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei you get nine. Of course here
there is an interesting part of the question because we really should
have ten because we really should
have מקדש ישראל ויום הזכרון. Mekadesh Yisrael VeYom HaZikaron. And what we
do in our שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei is we combine that ברכה
beracha about the יום yom with מלכויות. Malchuyot. We've מלך על כל
הארץ מקדש ישראל ויום הזכרון. Melech Al Kol HaAretz Mekadesh Yisrael VeYom
HaZikaron. And there's actually a debate of תנאים Tannaim how to take
what should be ten ברכות berachot and conflate it into nine. Where
and there are other answers to that question but everybody agrees you
have nine, you want to wind up with nine even though logically
you have the three beginning, the three at the end, מלכויות זכרונות
ושופרות Malchuyot Zichronot VeShofrot and קדושת היום. Kedushat HaYom.
So if you're counting and you look at the structure of that
עמידה Amidah it's confusing actually for that.
Right. And actually if you notice that the first ברכה beracha that
we do right which instead of הקל הקדוש HaKel HaKadosh is המלך
הקדוש HaMelech HaKadosh is because according to some that was the מלכויות.
Malchuyot. Exactly. So that's why some right exactly and part of that
is trying to get ten ברכות berachot into nine. So here why
we focus on need for nine is definitely a good question. Let's
see what the answer is. So כנגד מי? keneged mi? אמר רבי
יוסף Amar Rabbi Yosef דמי demi כנגד
קרטיגנין. keneged kartignin. I don't know what this carset. Anyway, כנגד ט'
אזכרות שאמרה חנה בתפלתה, keneged tesha azkarot she'amra Chana b'tefilatah,
opposite the nine, the nine times God's name appears in חנה's Chana
prayer. דאמר מר, De'amar Mar, and here we make, here it's much
clearer than the Kol Bo answer before, בראש השנה נפקדו שרה רחל
וחנה, B'Rosh Hashana nifkadu Sarah Rachel v'Chana, she was remembered, שרה רחל
וחנה Sarah Rachel v'Chana were all remembered by God on ראש השנה,
Rosh Hashana, and that's why we have that as the הפטרה haftarah
and therefore it is opposite that. Again, you know, it seems a
little weak. It doesn't seem that חנה's Chana תפילה tefila is a
central theme to ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana, so it's interesting to look
for symbolism and the answers are not so like they don't blow
you out of the water. Anyway, what's that? That's what I was
saying. It might mean, that's what I just said before with the...
yeah, but God didn't answer her prayer just on the one... on
ראש השנה. Rosh Hashana. Yeah, but she gave birth, right.
Or she became pregnant, meaning she became pregnant
because she was there for the
רגל. regel.
Right. But when it says וה' פקד, v'Hashem pakad, when it says
פקד, pakad, it presumably normally means remembered and it's assumed to mean
that's when she conceived. Okay, so when it says וה' פקד את
שרה v'Hashem pakad et Sarah and we say that was ראש השנה,
Rosh Hashana, it means when she conceived.
Okay. הני עשרין וארבע דתעניתא כנגד מי? Hani esrin v'arba d'taanita keneged
mi? How about the twenty-four of תענית? taanit? I bet you didn't
know there were twenty-four ברכות brachot in שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei in
תענית. taanit. You have your normal eighteen plus they add six special,
this is for תענית ציבור, taanit tzibur, not that we do for
like תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, but this is when they would have
a תענית taanit for issues about rain and so on. They would
add six ברכות brachot to the שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei to get
twenty-four. So again, we want to somehow assume there's some symbolism. So
אמר רבי חלבו Amar Rabbi Chelbo כנגד כ"ד רננות שאמר שלמה בשעה
שהכניס ארון לבית קדשי הקדשים. keneged chaf-dalet renanot she'amar Shlomo besha'ah she'hichnis
aron l'Beit Kadshei HaKadashim. When שלמה Shlomo said his prayer when they
were bringing the ארון aron into the קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kadashim, he
said twenty-four language of רננות. renanot. It's not also the word רננה,
renana, I think רש"י Rashi there
says רינה תפילה תחנה, rina tefila techina, it's different types of language
of prayer, song, and rejoicing and you count all those different words
he used for prayer and it's twenty-four. So the גמרא Gemara says
אי הכי כל יומא נמי נימרינהו. ee hachi kol yoma nami nimrinhu.
So the first time the גמרא Gemara actually asks this, but that's
actually a general idea. If prayer can be referred to in twenty-four
different terms or it says it twenty-four times, that's a general idea
of prayer, and if you look at שמואל's Shmuel prayer, it's not
unique to תענית. taanit. I mean, שמואל's Shmuel prayer is about that
everybody will now pray towards you, towards the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash,
and if somebody finds themselves in a faraway land and they have
to pray to you, they'll direct their prayers towards the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. It's a general sort of prayer about prayer. So why
should if it's about twenty-four, shouldn't all prayer have twenty-four? So the
גמרא Gemara says
אימא דאמרינהו שלמה ביומא דרחמי. eima de'amrinhu Shlomo b'yoma de'rachmei. No, שלמה
Shlomo said it in a time of particular, a time where it
was of God's compassion, they were bringing the ארון aron into the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, the heavens were open and therefore he used
all these different language. אנן נמי ביומא דרחמי אמרינן להו. anan nami
b'yoma de'rachmei amrinan lehu. We also say it in a time of
compassion. Of course it's interesting, we say it at a time when
we're seeking compassion. He said it presumably at a time when God
was already showing compassion. But if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י
Rashi tries to combine the two and he says ביומא דרחמי שהוצרך
לבקש רחמים שדבקו שערים זה בזה. b'yoma de'rachmei she'hutzrach l'vakesh rachamim she'davku
shearim zeh bazeh. So he quotes a מדרש Midrash which is when
they tried to bring the ארון aron in, the gates were like
wouldn't open, they were closed, they locked to one another, and שלמה
Shlomo had to make a special בקשה bakasha to God and finally
he says open the gates for דוד David my father and then
the gates opened so everybody could see that although דוד David couldn't
have built the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, in the end the gates
were opened because of the זכות zechut of דוד. David. So רש"י
Rashi brings that מדרש Midrash because otherwise it doesn't make sense. שלמה's
Shlomo prayer is at a time when God is already showing compassion
and we're saying the twenty-four ברכות brachot at a time when we
actually are not having rain and feel God hasn't had compassion and
are praying for God's compassion. So רש"י Rashi tries to bring the
two together. Okay, so that is the end of the various symbolisms
and now we continue in the גמרא. Gemara. רבי יהושע אומר מעין
שמונה עשרה. Rabbi Yehoshua omer me'ein Shemoneh Esrei. So now we get
to this debate about whether you say the full eighteen or you
say a digest of the eighteen. Or רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
if you know how to do it well then you say the
full, if you don't know how to do it well you say
the digest. And remember of course we're talking in the time when
they had they did not people were basically not literate and they
didn't have too much written down either, so not everybody it was
not taken for granted that people knew how to say the שמונה
עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. There were no סידורים.
siddurim. And there were no סידורים, siddurim, correct.
So the גמרא Gemara says מאי מעין שמונה עשרה? mai me'ein Shemoneh
Esrei? What does it mean that you can say a distillation of
the שמונה עשרה? Shemoneh Esrei? רב אמר מעין כל ברכה וברכה. Rav
amar me'ein kol bracha u'bracha. You can say a short version of
each ברכה. bracha. You still say eighteen ברכות, brachot, but you say
a short version of it. So you say ברוך אתה ה', Baruch
Atah Hashem, you know, חונן הדעת, Chonen HaDaat, ברוך אתה ה', Baruch
Atah Hashem, you know, המרבה לסלוח. HaMarbeh L'isloach. Maybe you say half
a sentence before the ברכה, bracha, but you have to say the
eighteen ברכות. brachot. Okay. ושמואל אמר, U'Shmuel amar, שמואל Shmuel said הביננו
ה' אלוהינו. Havineinu Hashem Elokeinu. He has a ברכה bracha called הביננו.
Havineinu. does not have a separate ברכה bracha for all the middle
ones, basically it mentions all of the middle things but does not
have a separate ברכה bracha for each of the middle ברכות. brachot.
And here's what it is: הביננו ה׳ אלהינו לדעת דרכך. Havineinu Hashem
Elokeinu ladaat derachecha. So you start with the first three, you have
the last three, but for the middle twelve or thirteen you basically
have just two words essentially for each ברכה. bracha. And here's what
you say for the middle twelve. Okay, הביננו ה׳ אלהינו לדעת דרכך,
Havineinu Hashem Elokeinu ladaat derachecha, let us know your ways, which is
חונן הדעת, Chonen HaDaat, ומול לבבנו ליראתך, umols l'veinu yiratecha, you know,
circumcise our hearts to fear you, which is השיבנו, Hashiveinu, right? ותסלח
לנו, Vatislach lanu, to forgive us, right? Which is, which is, which
is ברכת סליחה, birchat slichah, להיות גאולים, lihyot geulim, which is גואל
ישראל, Goel Yisrael, והרחיקנו ממכאובינו, viharchekeinu mimachoveinu, I should be looking at
a סידור, siddur, hold on, I'm just so confused here. Okay, yeah,
yeah, yeah. I'm just, I'm just sorry. I'm just, I can't multi-process
like this. Okay. Okay, so all right, fine. So we had חנון
המרבה לסלוח, Chanun Hamarbeh Lislioach, then it's גואל ישראל. Goel Yisrael. Now
it's, the next is רפאנו, Refaeinu, so it's והרחיקנו ממכאובינו, viharchekeinu mimachoveinu,
distance us from our, from our pains, from our sufferings. That's רופא
חולי עמו ישראל. Rofeh cholei amo Yisrael. ודשננו בנאות ארצך, Vidashneinu binot
artzecha, make us sort of a lush, a like flourishing in the,
in the dwelling of your land. So that's מברך השנים. Mivarech Hashanim.
ונפוצותינו מארבע תקבץ, Unfutzoiseinu mearba tikabetz, so that's מקבץ נדחי עמו ישראל,
Mekabetz nidchei amo Yisrael, gather the dispersed. והתועים על דעתך ישפוטו, Vehatoim
al daat-cha yishpotu, those that go, that sway from your, that sway
that go off of your path, go against your will, they should
be judged. So that's מלך אוהב צדקה ומשפט. Melech ohev tzedakah umishpat.
ועל רשעים תניף ידך, Veal rishaim tanif yadecha, raise your hand against
the wicked, that's שובר אויבים ומכניע זדים. Shover oyvim umachnia zeidim. וישמחו
צדיקים בבנין עירך, Viyismechu tzadikim b'vinyan irecha, so that's משען ומבטח לצדיקים,
Mishaan umivtach latzadikim, but it's also ובתיקון היכלך, ubitikun heichalecha, ובצמיחת קרן
לדוד עבדך. ubitzmichat keren l'David avdecha. So we sort of, you know,
segue that into בונה ירושלים Boneh Yerushalayim and מצמיח קרן ישועה, Matzmiach
keren yeshua, צמיחת קרן לדוד עבדך, tzmichat keren l'David avdecha, right? So
the, the bringing of the Davidic monarchy. ובעריכת נר לבן ישי משיחך,
Uva'arichat ner l'ben Yishai meshichecha, actually it goes interestingly we go a
little bit more at length on that one. טרם נקרא אתה תענה,
Terem nikra Atah taaneh, before we call out you've already answer us.
ברוך אתה ה׳ שומע תפילה, Baruch Atah Hashem shomea tfila, which gets
you to שומע תפילה. shomea tfila. So there you go, in like
about twenty words we've now done all of the middle ברכות, brachot,
and then you do the last three. That really makes it a
lot easier, right? Okay. So, so now the גמרא Gemara says, so
that's your short one according to שמואל, Shmuel, which really makes it
much easier on people that can't memorize the whole thing. So לייט
עלה אביי אמאן דמצלי הביננו, Layeit ala Abaye amand'matzlei Havineinu, אביי Abaye
used to curse somebody who would say הביננו, Havineinu, which means technically
it's okay, you're יוצא, yotzei, there are different opinions in the משנה,
Mishna, but he would sort of say, you know, that is really
not the right way to דאוון. daven. If you're serious about it,
you're not going to say הביננו. Havineinu. Yes. On the phrase והתועים
על דעתך ישפוטו, vehatoim al daat-cha yishpotu, that's going on the judges,
השיבה שופטינו כבראשונה, Hashivah shofteinu k'varishona, that's the ones, that the judges
who err in judgment they should, they should judge correctly or they
should be judged. But that they should judge correctly I think because
that's the theme. Well רש״י Rashi says, if you look at רש״י,
Rashi, רש״י Rashi has two, two versions on it. רש״י Rashi says
התועים על דעתך העוברים על דבריך ישפוטו, hatoim al daat-cha haovrim al
dvarecha yishpotu, right, מלך אוהב צדקה ומשפט. Melech ohev tzedakah umishpat. And
then it says לשון אחר, lashon achar, התועים במשפט על דעתך ישפוטו,
hatoim bemishpat al daat-cha yishpotu, so which is what you're saying. Those
that mistakenly judge, help them judge according to your, the correct judgment,
right? That's what you're saying. So רש״י Rashi has both approaches. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so אביי Abaye did
not like it. And that's our basic approach. We basically say that
unless there's a special, a special, a special reason you should say
the full שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. So now אמר רב נחמן אמר
שמואל כל השנה כולה מתפלל אדם הביננו. Amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel
kol hashanah kulo mitpallel adam Havineinu. Really, against אביי, Abaye, you can
say הביננו Havineinu the entire year if you want to. חוץ ממוצאי
שבת ומוצאי יום טוב, Chutz mimotzaei Shabbat umotzaei Yom Tov, you only
have to say the normal שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei when it's מוצאי
שבת motzaei Shabbat and מוצאי יום טוב. motzaei Yom Tov. Why? מפני
שצריך לומר הבדלה בחונן הדעת, mipnei shetzarich lomar Havdala b'Chonen HaDaat, because
you have to say הבדלה Havdala in חונן הדעת, Chonen HaDaat, you
have to do an insertion. Well now here is going to come
the question: what happens if you're saying הביננו Havineinu and there are
times where you have to do insertions, right? יעלה ויבוא, Yaaleh V'Yavo,
you know, הבדלה. Havdala. So he says right, on those days if
you have to do הבדלה Havdala you have to say the full
שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. So מתקיף לה רבא בר שמואל ונימרי ברכה
רביעית בפני עצמה, matkif lah Rava bar Shmuel vneimarei bracha revii bifnei
atzma, why not just say a fourth ברכה? bracha? To do do
חונן הדעת Chonen HaDaat separately and then do the, then do הביננו?
Havineinu? So וכי לא תנינא, v'chi lo tnina, didn't we say רבי
עקיבא אומר אומר ברכה רביעית בפני עצמה, Rebbi Akiva omer omer bracha
revii bifnei atzma, רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says in general the הבדלה
Havdala in שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei is a separate ברכה. bracha. It
is not, it is not incorporated into חונן הדעת. Chonen HaDaat. רבי
אליעזר אומר בהודאה, Rebbi Eliezer omer behodah, רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer says
you stick it into מודים. Modim. So there's actually a whole range
of opinions about where you say הבדלה. Havdalah. So therefore, so if
we can't fit it into the text of הביננו, Havinnenu, fine, let's
just make it a separate ברכה. Beracha. So the גמרא Gemara says
one minute. אטו כל השנה כולה נעביד כרבי עקיבא דהתם נמי נעביד?
Atu kol hashanah kullah ne'avid ke-Rabbi Akiva de-hasam nami ne'avid? Very convenient
that you're suggesting, but we don't פסק pasken like רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva in general. In general, we don't say הבדלה Havdalah as a
separate ברכה Beracha in שמנה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. We incorporate it into
חונן הדעת. Chonen Hada'as. So what now makes you think we're entitled
to rule like רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? So the גמרא Gemara says
one minute. כל השנה כולה מאי טעמא לא עבדינן כרבי עקיבא? Kol
hashanah kullah mai ta'ama la avdinan ke-Rabbi Akiva? Why do we normally
not rule like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and make it a separate
ברכה? Beracha? התם תמני סרי תקון תשסרי לא תקון. Hasam temanei srei
tikkun teshasrei lo tikkun. We established 18 and not 19. We don't
add ברכות. Berachos. Of course there's an irony in this because we
do have 19, but okay, whatever, our number is our number. We
don't go adding ברכות. Berachos. הכא נמי שבע תקון תמני לא תקון.
Hacha nami sheva tikkun temanei lo tikkun. So here too, same thing
applies. We have seven if you allow הביננו. Havinnenu. It means we
established a seven-ברכה Beracha שמנה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei with הביננו, Havinnenu, and
we don't have an eight-ברכה Beracha שמנה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. We're not
going to go ahead and and make it and make it different.
So the גמרא Gemara says מתקיף לה מר זוטרא ונכללה מכלל הביננו.
Maskif lah Mar Zutra venichlolah michlal Havinnenu. Why don't, why not just
incorporate it into the הביננו Havinnenu text? What should we say? הביננו
ה' אלהינו המבדיל בין קדש לחול. Havinnenu Hashem Elokeinu hamavdil bein kodesh
le-chol. Just stick in the words המבדיל בין קדש לחול. hamavdil bein
kodesh le-chol. Let us understand you, you know, and you God who
is המבדיל בין קדש לחול, hamavdil bein kodesh le-chol, and then continue
with the rest of the text. קשיא. Kashya. Okay, that's a good
question. Somehow we assume that we have this sort of digest of
הביננו, Havinnenu, but we don't have the ability to make insertions into
it. So since when you need to make an insertion like you
need to say הבדלה, Havdalah, since you can't add a ברכה Beracha
and you can't make an insertion, insertion, you have to go back
to your standard full שמנה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. That's the whole tension
that continues throughout the development of this, correct? In other words, you
have like during עשרת ימי תשובה, Aseres Yemei Teshuvah, discussion about insertions
that we take for granted. Exactly. That you have insertions. Right. Right.
Of certain insertions. Right. Those are מקובל. mekubal. Right. Right. Well, it's
certainly true that insertions post the גמרא Gemara met with a lot
of resistance and there was a lot of debate about that at
the time of the גאונים. Geonim. And did the גאונים Geonim have
a right to make insertions particularly in the first three and last
three ברכות? Berachos? In the middle ברכות, Berachos, there was always a
certain amount of latitude even for an individual to make insertions. But
here what the גמרא Gemara is saying is, here it's the גמרא
Gemara that's establishing the insertions, saying they made the insertions where they
already exist. So here the question of why not make insertions in
הביננו Havinnenu is a pretty good question. I mean we've made insertions
in חונן הדעת, Chonen Hada'as, let's make insertions in הביננו. Havinnenu. And
the גמרא Gemara does not really have a good answer. As we'll
see later, it might be that the whole point is that this
is a text for people that don't know the שמנה עשרה Shemoneh
Esrei well, and you start fiddling with it and it gets too
confusing. Of course, I don't know how it makes it any better
that saying that then you have to say the full שמנה עשרה,
Shemoneh Esrei, but okay, maybe you say the full שמנה עשרה, Shemoneh
Esrei, you're listening along with somebody else, I don't know. But you
know, if you're trying to keep the text relatively simple, you don't
want to start fudging with it. Is it true to say that
הביננו Havinnenu could be said all year round? That's a good question.
For those that say you can say it all year round and
you don't need a special exception, maybe, maybe. I don't know. I
mean, since we don't rule this way, you know, as a general
rule, so it doesn't come up that much. Yes. We do have
an abbreviated שמנה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei on Friday night. About, yeah, about
the, right, about the, what do you call it? The, the thing
right afterwards, מגן אבות, Magen Avos, right, right. So that, and you're
saying that that is a type of a הביננו Havinnenu that we
have on Friday night. Yeah, that's an interesting parallel. Although it's for
a different purpose. Right, right. That's an interesting parallel. Okay. So now
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. It's going to continue on
this theme. אמר חביבי בר אביי כל השנה כולה מתפלל אדם הביננו.
Amar Havivi bar Abaye kol hashanah kullah mispallel adam Havinnenu. So you
can say, maybe you, you can say it the whole year, חוץ
מימות הגשמים. chutz mi-ymos hageshamim. But you can't say it the whole
year except for half of the year. Except for the rainy period,
which is basically from סוכות Succos or ז' מרחשון Zayin Mar-Cheshvan until
פסח. Pesach. So basically it's half of the year. Why can't you
say it at that time? מפני שצריך לומר שאלה בברכת השנים. mipnei
she-tzarich lomar she'eilah be-virchas hashanim. Because you have to say ותן טל
ומטר לברכה, vesen tal u-matar livracha, and that's not part of the
fixed text of the הביננו. Havinnenu. So the obvious question is going
to be, מתקיף לה מר זוטרא ונכללה מכלל... maskif lah Mar Zutra
venichlolah michlal... why not include it, incorporate it into the text? ודשננו
בנאות ארצך ותן טל ומטר. ve-dashnenu bine'os artzecha vesen tal u-matar. Just
stick those three words ותן טל ומטר vesen tal u-matar in when
you say give us, you know, the, sort of the, the flourishing
of the land. So it says, אמרי אתי לאטרודי. amri ati le-itroudi.
No, then you'll get distracted and confused and you'll get and it'll
just it'll just make a mess of things. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אי הכי הבדלה בחונן הדעת נמי אתי לאטרודי? ei hachi Havdalah
be-Chonen Hada'as nami ati le-itroudi? Why don't you give that answer when
we said making the change in the beginning of it by הבדלה?
Havdalah? So no, אמרי התם כיון דאתי בתחלת צלותיה לא מטריד. amri
hasam keivan de-asi bis-chillas tzlusei lo matrid. There it's right at the
beginning of the text, right? Where it's הביננו לדעת דרכיך Havinnenu lada'as
derachecha you know המבדיל בין קדש לחול. hamavdil bein kodesh le-chol. So
there it's right at the beginning, you don't get confused. לא מטריד.
lo matrid. הכא כיון דאתי באמצע צלותיה מטריד. hacha keivan de-asi be-emtza
tzlusei matrid. That'll get you confused once you start, you know, you
know, fiddling with the text. All right. So מתקיף לה רבה. maskif
lah Rabbah. ונימרה בשומע תפילה, veneimrah beshomea tefilla, how about putting it
in שומע תפילה? shomea tefilla? דאמר רב תנחום אמר רב אסי, de'amar
Rav Tanchum amar Rav Assi, טעה ולא הזכיר גבורות גשמים בתחיית המתים
מחזירין אותו, ta'ah velo hizkir gevurot geshamim bitchiyat hametim machzirin oto, שאילה
בברכת השנים אין מחזירין אותו. she'eila bebirchat hashanim ein machzirin oto. Somebody
forgot to say משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם Mashiv Haruach Umorid Hageshem in
the first three ברכות, brachot, then you make them go back, because
any mistake in the first three you have to go back. If
however you forgot to say ותן טל ומטר V'tein Tal Umatar in
the ברכה bracha of ברכת השנים, Birchat Hashanim, then you do not
make them go back. Why? No, you don't make them go back
at all, but מפני שיכול לומרה בשומע תפילה. mipnei sheyachol lomrah beshomea
tefilla. Because in שומע תפילה, shomea tefilla, שומע תפילה shomea tefilla is
like a catch-all and you can add
in שומע תפילה shomea tefilla ותן טל ומטר לברכה.
V'tein Tal Umatar Livracha. You can add in requests that you forgot.
So if you missed something earlier, sometimes it's possible to say it
like if you miss הבדלה Havdala earlier you can say it in
שומע תפילה, shomea tefilla, if you miss ותן טל ומטר V'tein Tal
Umatar you can say it in שומע תפילה. shomea tefilla. Why can't
you say משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם Mashiv Haruach Umorid Hageshem in שומע
תפילה? shomea tefilla? Well two reasons. Number one is mistakes in the
first three we anyway we make you go back, those are much
more you know they those much more have to be exact in
their way. Number two is that ותן טל ומטר לברכה V'tein Tal
Umatar Livracha is not a בקשה. bakasha. שומע תפילה shomea tefilla is
where you add בקשות, bakashot, where you add requests. Something that you're
supposed to say that doesn't have the form of a בקשה, bakasha,
you cannot do in שומע תפילה. shomea tefilla. So anyway, so we
see that you can do it in שומע תפילה. shomea tefilla. So
why not here too? So the גמרא Gemara says one minute. טעה
ולא הזכיר גבורות גשמים בתחיית המתים מחזירין אותו שאילה בברכת השנים אין
מחזירין אותו מפני שיכול לומרה בשומע תפילה והבדלה בחונן הדעת אין מחזירין
אותו מפני שיכול לומרה על הכוס. Ta'ah velo hizkir gevurot geshamim bitchiyat
hametim machzirin oto she'eila bebirchat hashanim ein machzirin oto mipnei sheyachol lomrah
beshomea tefilla vehavdala bechonen hadaat ein machzirin oto mipnei sheyachol lomrah al
hakos. And if הבדלה Havdala if you forgot it, even if you
forgot it completely, you don't have to repeat שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei
because you're going to say it later על הכוס. al hakos. Okay,
so this is the general rule about when you have to go
back. So if you've got a question about ברכת השנים, Birchat Hashanim,
why don't we just stick it in שומע תפילה? shomea tefilla? So
גמרא Gemara says no, טעה שאני. ta'ah shani. If you make a
mistake then we allow you to do it in שומע תפילה, shomea
tefilla, but not from the very outset going to let you do
it in שומע תפילה. shomea tefilla. And since there's nowhere to say
ברכת השנים Birchat Hashanim of ותן טל ומטר, V'tein Tal Umatar, since
there's nowhere to say ותן טל ומטר לברכה V'tein Tal Umatar Livracha
during the rainy season, we could do not let you say הביננו,
Havineinu, we have you have to say the full שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh
Esrei. Okay, so now having gone from saying you can say הביננו
Havineinu the entire year, once you say you can't say it when
you have to say ותן טל ומטר, V'tein Tal Umatar, you're only
saying it half the year. I have to say though I don't
exactly understand the question of say it in שומע תפילה shomea tefilla
because in the standard הביננו, Havineinu, שומע תפילה shomea tefilla is not
a separate ברכה. bracha. The ברכה bracha ends with ברוך אתה ה'
שומע תפילה. Baruch ata Hashem shomea tefilla. But presumably what it means
is that you say you suggest making a change at the beginning.
By חונן הדעת Chonen Hadaat you could add הבדלה, Havdala, because when
you make a change at the beginning you don't get confused. So
what it's saying is okay, so insert it at the end. Don't
insert it in the middle where ברכת השנים Birchat Hashanim then you'll
get confused. But when you're getting right up to the חתימה chatima
ברוך אתה ה' שומע תפילה, Baruch ata Hashem shomea tefilla, right before
there say ותן טל ומטר לברכה, V'tein Tal Umatar Livracha, ברוך אתה
ה' שומע תפילה. Baruch ata Hashem shomea tefilla. So if you insert
it right at the end you won't get confused. And the answer
is okay, nevertheless we don't let you put it with שומע תפילה
shomea tefilla unless you've made a mistake. This idea of that we're
not going to insert to get confused right seems to also have
application fit the Sephardic practice at מוסף Musaf for יום טוב Yom
Tov is not to say the קרבנות. Korbanot. We don't say the
קרבנות. Korbanot. We don't specify like on סוכות. Sukkot. Right. And the
reason that's brought if I remember correctly the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch
brings because you're gonna make a mistake. I mean there's so many
so much of the rest of the שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. It's
the details so they don't say. ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh repeats in
general so we say. Right right right. There is that general concern
about you know you're absolutely right that's an ongoing concern about what
types of changes and again particularly assuming when people are דאווענינג davening
from סידורים siddurim that we can allow without undermining our whole enterprise.
That is correct. Okay, and did you say that we would say
הביננו Havineinu even במוצאי שבת bemotzei shabbat when you forgot? Presumably he
wasn't bothered with that. So where would he say ותן טל ומטר
לברכה V'tein Tal Umatar Livracha is not clear right. Maybe he would
add it in שומע תפילה. shomea tefilla. It's not clear exactly. You're
right why was he less bothered with that than he was with
like the חונן הדעת? Chonen Hadaat? Maybe because he wanted to give
you the option. Make a good point that if שמואל Shmuel was
bothered with the with הבדלה Havdala why was he not bothered with
the ותן טל ומטר. V'tein Tal Umatar. And my my gut is
that the answer is because he wanted to give people as much
option as possible to say הביננו. Havineinu. So to say מוצאי שבת
Motzei Shabbat not is one thing but to take out half a
year is a very different thing and maybe there he would have
allowed it to be towards the end in שומע תפילה. shomea tefilla.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues let's take a look. It
says: גופא. Gufa. אמר רב תנחום Amar Rav Tanchum now we get
to this question about missing something and making it up. אמר רב
אסי Amar Rav Assi טעה ולא הזכיר גבורות גשמים בתחיית המתים מחזירין
אותו. ta'ah velo hizkir gevurot geshamim bitchiyat hametim machzirin oto. If somebody
did not mention מחיה mechayeh גבורות גשמים gevurot geshamim משיב הרוח ומוריד
הגשם Mashiv Haruach Umorid Hageshem then you make them go back. שאילה
בברכת השנים אין מחזירין אותו she'eila bebirchat hashanim ein machzirin oto but
if they did not say ותן טל ומטר לברכה V'tein Tal Umatar
Livracha you do not make them go back. Why? מפני שיכול לומרה
בשומע תפילה mipnei sheyachol lomrah beshomea tefilla because you can say it
in שומע תפילה. shomea tefilla. הבדלה בחונן הדעת אין מחזירין אותו Havdala
bechonen hadaat ein machzirin oto if you miss הבדלה Havdala you don't
make them go back מפני שיכול לומרה על הכוס mipnei sheyachol lomrah
al hakos because you can say it when you're making הבדלה על
הכוס Havdalah al hakos on the cup of wine. מיתיבי: Meitivei: טעה
ולא הזכיר גבורות גשמים בתחיית המתים מחזירין אותו. Ta'ah velo hizkir gevurot
geshamim bitchiyat hametim machzirin oto. We have a ברייתא braita that... says
that if you did not mention משיב הרוח Mashiv HaRuach in the
תחיית המתים Techiyas HaMeisim in the second ברכה, bracha, you make them
go back. ושאלה בברכת השנים מחזירין אותו, V'she'eila b'virchas hashanim machzirin oso,
and similarly, if you do not say ותן טל ומטר לברכה, v'ten
tal u'matar livracha, you make them go back. והבדלה בחונן הדעת אין
מחזירין אותו, V'havdalah b'Chonen HaDaat ein machzirin oso, the one thing you
don't make them go back for is הבדלה, Havdala מפני שיכול לאומרה
על הכוס, mipnei she'yachol l'omrah al hakos, cause that you can say
when you're making הבדלה Havdalah, on a cup of wine. So how
do you deal with that contradiction? So the גמרא Gemara says, do
you make them go, somebody go back for ותן טל ומטר v'ten
tal u'matar or not? So the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא, lo
kashya, that's not difficult. הא ביחיד הא בציבור, Ha b'yachid ha b'tzibbur,
it's a difference whether you're דאוונינג davening privately or in a ציבור,
tzibbur, which is fascinating. בציבור מאי טעמא לא? B'tzibbur mai ta'ama lo?
Why do you not make somebody go back in the ציבור? tzibbur?
משום דשמע משליח ציבור, mishum d'shamei mishliach tzibbur, you'll be able to
hear it from the שליח ציבור, shliach tzibbur, even if you made
a mistake in your שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, you can be יוצא
yotzei through the שליח ציבור shliach tzibbur שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. The
גמרא Gemara says, one minute. אי הכי, Ei hachi, if that's why
you're not going to make them go back, מפני שיכול לאומרה בשומע
תפילה, mipnei she'yachol l'omrah b'Shomea Tefillah, it shouldn't be that you don't
make them go back because you can add it in שומע תפילה.
Shomea Tefillah. מפני ששומע מתפילת ציבור מיבעי ליה, Mipnei she'shomea m'tefillas tzibbur
miba'ei lei, you should say don't make him go back because you'll
just hear it from the שליח ציבור. shliach tzibbur. So we should
stop and notice that this is the first time the גמרא Gemara
has told us that you could be יוצא yotzei your שמונה עשרה
Shmoneh Esrei by listening to the שליח ציבור. shliach tzibbur. Now that's
really why they established the שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, but we no
longer really think of it that much in those terms. But here,
and normally we think of it they established the שליח ציבור shliach
tzibbur for somebody who didn't know how to דאוון. davven. Here we're
seeing a possibility that okay, you know how to דאוון, davven, you
made a mistake, we don't make you go back, just listen to
the שליח ציבור. shliach tzibbur. So we should just stop and note
that that's important, the assumptions of this גמרא, Gemara, that you can
be יוצא yotzei if you made a mistake by listening to the
שליח ציבור. shliach tzibbur. But the גמרא Gemara is now saying that
can't be פשט. pshat. If that were פשט, pshat, it wouldn't say
because you could put it into שומע תפילה, Shomea Tefillah, it would
have said you don't go back because you'll just listen to the
שליח ציבור. shliach tzibbur. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא אידי ואידי
ביחיד, ella idi v'idi b'yachid, fine, you're right. We're not talking that
you can hear from the שליח ציבור. shliach tzibbur. If you can
hear from the שליח ציבור, shliach tzibbur, maybe that would be fine,
but that's not what we're talking about. ולא קשיא, V'lo kashya, here's
the difference why one says you go back and one says you
don't. הא דאדכר קודם שומע תפילה הא דאדכר בתר שומע תפילה, Ha
d'adkar kodem Shomea Tefillah ha d'adkar basar Shomea Tefillah, very simple answer.
Did you remember that you forgot before you hit שומע תפילה? Shomea
Tefillah? Then insert it into שומע תפילה. Shomea Tefillah. But sometimes you
only wake up after you said שומע תפילה Shomea Tefillah and you
realize you forgot. In that case, you can no longer insert it
into שומע תפילה Shomea Tefillah and you have to go back and
do the entire שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, which by the way, you
know, explains the הבדלה Havdalah case. Why didn't they say by הבדלה,
Havdalah don't go back for הבדלה, Havdalah, you can say it in
שומע תפילה? Shomea Tefillah? Well, if you're talking that you have forgotten
the whole thing, you finished שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei and you realize
you forgot, so then by ותן טל ומטר, v'ten tal u'matar, you
have to go back, but by הבדלה, Havdalah, you don't have to
go back because you can say הבדלה על הכוס. Havdalah al hakos?
Okay, הלכה למעשה, Halacha l'ma'aseh, what if you make הבדלה Havdalah, על
הכוס al hakos before you דאוון davven מעריב? Maariv? You still say
it in מעריב. Maariv. It would still so, but he says though,
it's not exactly logical why you should. You'd be יוצא yotzei without
it, but it doesn't mean that you're no, that that it obviates
the need for saying it. חז"ל Chazal were מתקן, mesaken, what is
the nature of the need of saying it if you've made הבדלה
Havdalah על הכוס? al hakos. Because הבדלה Havdalah in שמונה עשרה Shmoneh
Esrei is not just a way to be יוצא yotzei הבדלה, Havdalah,
it's also the general theme of שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei which is
about בכל יום תן לו מעין ברכותיו, b'chol yom ten lo mei'ein
birchosav, that שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei should always sort of be reflecting
the period in which it's being said. So, for example, even if
you, if you miss יעלה ויבא Ya'aleh V'yavo on ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh on מעריב, Maariv, you don't go back, but it's not all
determined by what you sort of, of course that's different because you
didn't do it in some other way. But you're right, הבדלה Havdalah
in שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei is not just a vehicle for saying
הבדלה. Havdalah. הבדלה Havdalah in שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei is מוצאי שבת,
Motzaei Shabbos, it should reflect the fact it adds more, it reflects
דעת, daat, it reflects, and it right, it should reflect what this
time is about. This is a time of distinguishing קודש kodesh and
חול, chol, that should be reflected in the שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei,
exactly. But you're right, it does have both elements. If it was
only an act for the שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, you wouldn't say
you make it up in you do it in הבדלה. Havdalah. So
there are those, it's an excellent point, there are both of those
aspects to it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר רב תנחום אמר רב אסי אמר רב יהושע בן לוי, Amar
Rav Tanchum amar Rav Assi amar Rav Yehoshua ben Levi, top of
כט עמוד ב, kaf-tes amud beis, says רב תנחום אמר רב אסי
אמר רב יהושע בן לוי: Rav Tanchum amar Rav Assi amar Rav
Yehoshua ben Levi: טעה ולא הזכיר של ראש חודש בעבודה חוזר לעבודה.
T'ah v'lo hizkir shel Rosh Chodesh b'avodah chozer l'avodah. If you forgot
to say, here we just mentioned it, יעלה ויבא Ya'aleh V'yavo in
רצה Retzei in the עבודה Avodah on ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, you
go back to רצה. Retzei. נזכר בהודאה חוזר לעבודה. Nizkar b'hoda'ah chozer
l'avodah. If you remembered by מודים, Modim, right, that you forgot to
say יעלה ויבא, Ya'aleh V'yavo, go back to רצה. Retzei. בשים שלום
חוזר לעבודה. B'sim shalom chozer l'avodah. You remembered at שים שלום Sim
Shalom that you got to say יעלה ויבא, Ya'aleh V'yavo, חוזר לעבודה,
chozer l'avodah, so you go back to רצה. Retzei. ואם סיים, V'im
siyeim, so until you are, now this is interesting because we had
just said, notice the חידוש chiddush here, we should stop and notice
the חידוש, chiddush, that if you missed saying let's say, you know,
ותן טל ומטר לברכה, v'ten tal u'matar livracha, you can insert it
in שומע תפילה. Shomea Tefillah. Once you've said שומע תפילה, Shomea Tefillah,
you have to go back to the entire שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei.
So logically, you would have said once you missed saying יעלה ויבא
Ya'aleh V'yavo in רצה, Retzei, so you missed the right ברכה, bracha,
you can't say it in a later ברכה, bracha, so presumably you
have to go back all the way to the beginning. And here
the interesting thing is we're allowing you to go back to the
ברכה bracha that you missed, רצה, Retzei, and continue from there. Okay,
so, now ואם סיים, V'im siyeim, if you finished the whole שמנה
עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, then חוזר לראש, chozer l'rosh, then you have to
do the whole thing again once you missed יעלה ויבא. Ya'aleh V'Yavo.
אמר רב פפה בריה דרב אחא בר אדא, Amar Rav Papa brei
d'Rav Acha bar Adda, הא דאמרן סיים חוזר לראש, ha d'amran siyeim
chozer l'rosh, when we said if you finished you go back to
the beginning, לא אמרן אלא שעקר רגליו, lo amran ela she'akar raglav,
it's only when you uprooted your legs. אבל לא עקר רגליו חוזר
לעבודה, Aval lo akar raglav chozer l'avoda, but even if you've somehow
finished and you haven't moved your legs, you can go back to
the עבודה. avoda. Now what does עקר רגליו akar raglav mean? So
there's an interesting debate about in the פוסקים poskim whether it's literal,
which is presumably what it means, that you've taken steps back. And
that's very important because that means that conceptually even before you've stepped
back, you're still considered עומד לפני המקום omeid lifnei hamakom and somehow
in the presence of God even though you've finished your שמנה עשרה
Shmoneh Esrei before you step back. It's very relevant for this time
of year where there's an, I, where we say וידוי Vidui at
the end of שמנה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, right, and on יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, and the, it's supposed to be connected to the שמנה
עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, and but how, but is it really part of
the text of the שמנה עשרה? Shmoneh Esrei? And basically what we
do is we say it before we step back. We say it
while we're still considered to be עומד לפני המקום. omeid lifnei hamakom.
Now some say that it's not only the actual stepping back, it's
even a conceptual עקירה רגליו, akira raglav, and when you say like
יהיו לרצון אמרי פי והגיון לבי לפניך ה' צורי וגואלי, Yihyu l'ratzon
imrei fi v'hegyon libi lefanecha Hashem tzuri v'goali, which is what we
learned earlier was a state, you know, a פסוק pasuk added at
the end which basically says, "Okay, I'm done now," is essentially what
it says, "I've prayed, God please accept my prayer." So that constitutes
עקירה רגליו. akira raglav. So that has relevance both for this idea
of going back to רצה Retzei if you missed יעלה ויבא. Ya'aleh
V'Yavo. It also has relevance for whether you say that before after
you do the וידוי. Vidui. Some סידורים siddurim differ on that, but
I, but you know I'm of the opinion you should say the
וידוי Vidui and then do the יהיו לרצון Yihyu l'ratzon because you
want to have it sort of in that state of still being
עומד לפני המקום omeid lifnei hamakom which is clear from the גמרא
Gemara that they wanted to really have the וידוי Vidui somewhat very
much part of the שמנה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei without inserting it into
the שמנה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. So we're saying that according to everybody,
the fact that you said המברך את עמו ישראל בשלום Hamivarech et
amo Yisrael bashalom is not the point? Right, that well it's the
end of the שמנה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, but somehow you're, the way
I would phrase it is your שמנה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei is over
but you're still עומד לפני המקום. omeid lifnei hamakom. Now that's important
in terms of let's say the וידוי. Vidui. The interesting thing here
is, is that in some ways it's saying it's not fully over
yet because you're allowed to go back and fix it. If it
was fully over, you've done שמנה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, if you made
a mistake you've got to do the whole thing again. So this
is actually pushing it even a little further than just saying you're
in God's presence but you're done with שמנה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. To
some degree it's sort of like almost like a תוך כדי דיבור,
toch k'dei dibbur, because you haven't stepped out of that, out of
that mode yet, you can go back and correct. Okay, and that's
the amazing, the amazing thing of this גמרא Gemara and very relevant
להלכה. l'halacha. Okay, so אמר ליה, amar leh, אבל לא עקר רגליו
חוזר לעבודה. aval lo akar raglav chozer l'avoda. So the גמרא Gemara
says אמר ליה מנא לך הא, amar leh mna lach ha, where
do you know this from? אמר ליה מאבא מארי שמיעא לי, amar
leh me'abba mari shmi'a li, I heard it from אבא מארי, Abba
Mari, ואבא מארי מרב, v'Abba Mari me'Rav, and אבא מארי Abba Mari
heard it from רב. Rav. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak, הא דאמרן עקר רגליו חוזר לראש, ha d'amran akar
raglav chozer l'rosh, that which we said that once you move your
legs you have to go back to the beginning if you missed,
you know, יעלה ויבא, Ya'aleh V'Yavo, לא אמרן אלא שאינו רגיל לומר
תחנונים אחר תפילתו, lo amran ela she'eino ragil lomar tachanunim achar tefillato,
and here we get this idea how long does that sort of
שמנה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei status continue. If you don't normally say תחנונים,
tachanunim, you know sort of your personal supplications after you finish. But
one minute, אבל רגיל לומר תחנונים אחר תפילתו חוזר לעבודה, aval ragil
lomar tachanunim achar tefillato chozer l'avoda, if you normally say supplications, and
then you can go back. Let's look at רש"י Rashi what that
means. תחנונים, Tachanunim, רש"י Rashi says כגון אלקי נצור לשוני מרע k'gon
Elokai netzor leshoni meira שאנו אומרים בעמידה אחר תפילה. she'anu omrim ba'amida
achar tefilla. So if you normally say the אלקי נצור, Elokai netzor,
right, then that is then, then presumably even if you are עקר
רגליו akar raglav that you can then go back even because you
are still somewhat in the process of שמנה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. So
this is interesting, even presumably you literally stepped back but you're still
saying תחנונים, tachanunim, that somehow still puts you in that state of
שמנה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei and being able to go back. Okay, איכא
דאמרי, Ika d'amri, some say אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak, הא דאמרן כי לא עקר רגליו חוזר לעבודה. ha
d'amran ki lo akar raglav chozer l'avoda. That's the more מקיל meikil
way, what I was telling you earlier and what we're going to
conclude with is the more מחמיר machmir way. הא דאמרן כי לא
עקר רגליו חוזר לעבודה, Ha d'amran ki lo akar raglav chozer l'avoda,
when do we say when you haven't stepped back you're still in
the mode and you can still go back, לא אמרן אלא שרגיל
לומר תחנונים אחר תפילתו, lo amran ela sheragil lomar tachanunim achar tefillato,
that has to somehow be it's not just you haven't stepped back,
something still has to put you still in the process and still
in the presence there and being עומד לפני המקום, omeid lifnei hamakom,
that's only when you normally do say תחנונים. tachanunim. So you say
אלקי נשמה. Elokai neshama. So what it's describing now is you said
ברוך אתה ה' המברך את עמו ישראל בשלום, Baruch Atah Hashem hamivarech
et amo Yisrael bashalom, you haven't stepped back, but you know why
you're not done, you're not done not just because you haven't stepped
back, you're not done because you also haven't finished saying אלקי נצור
Elokai netzor and you normally say אלקי נצור. Elokai netzor. So the
fact that you still have something left to say, even though it's
your own personal thing left to say, and you haven't moved back,
that still puts you in this mode of still being in the
middle of שמנה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. By the way, I should say
this is all very powerful, going back to the earlier theme I
mentioned about the relationship of the sort of private and personal prayer
and the fixed prayer, here part of what extends the fixed prayer
is the fact that you are still have some private prayer that
you still need to be saying. Now again, it's not completely that
if just today you decided to say something that would not make
it an extension, it's that it's a regular part and then it
becomes incorporated, so your personal supplications when it's done on a regular
basis become incorporated and extends what it means to be עומד בתפילה.
Omed Bitfillah. So while the text is done, you are still considered
עומד בתפילה Omed Bitfillah as long as you have not stepped back
and you normally would be adding prayers right now. Okay, אבל אלו
הרגיל להתחנן אחר תפילתו, Aval elu ha-ragil l'hitchanen achar tfilato, אבל אם
אינו רגיל להתחנן אחר תפילתו, aval im eino ragil l'hitchanen achar tfilato,
if you normally don't add your own private prayers, then חוזר לראש
chozer lerosh even without stepping back, you're done. So one of two
things could make you done: you've physically moved out of the zone,
or you have nothing left to say. But if you haven't moved
out of the zone and you still normally would be saying things,
you're still in the mode of praying even though the text is
done, you still are in the process of prayer and you can
still be חוזר לראש. chozer lerosh. So again, very important both halakhically
and in terms of conceptually the merging of the private prayer and
the statutory prayer. But if there's no private supplications after the last
ברכה, bracha, aren't we supposed to say יהיו לרצון אמרי פי? Yihyu
leratzon imrei phi? Yes, and therefore even if you don't say, well
we also all say אלהי נצור Elokai Netzor as well, but yes,
therefore generally if you say יהיו לרצון, Yihyu leratzon, you're considered mostly
to sort of be over. Now we actually add a little paragraph
after the יהיו לרצון, Yihyu leratzon, right, don't we? Where's a סידור
siddur here? What do we say? We say יהיו לרצון Yihyu leratzon
and then עושה שלום במרומיו, Oseh shalom bimromav, ויהי רצון מלפניך ה׳
אלהינו שיבנה בית המקדש במהרה בימינו, v'yehi ratzon milfanecha Hashem Elokeinu she-yibaneh
beit ha-mikdash bimhera v'yameinu, da da da da da da. So there
is some, right, so there's some question whether that stuff we say
after the יהיו לרצון Yihyu leratzon still counts as עומד בתפילה Omed
Bitfillah or is the יהיו לרצון Yihyu leratzon basically a type of
עוקר רגליו. oker raglav. So if we were just to base ourselves
on the אומר תחנונים, omer tachanunim, so everybody says תחנונים tachanunim until
כימי עולם וכשנים קדמוניות, kimei olam u'cheshanim kadmoniyot, and we say until
you say all of that and step back. But some פוסקים poskim
do say that since יהיו לרצון Yihyu leratzon has basically a statement
of like I'm done, right, it's pretty much implicit in the יהיו
לרצון, Yihyu leratzon, that that might constitute a type of עוקר רגליו.
oker raglav. Okay, so that's a little bit of a question of
what the story is after you say the יהיו לרצון. Yihyu leratzon.
And the aspect of the embodiment of prayer, basically, along with the
וכל עצמותי תאמרנה, v'chol atzmotai tomarnah, is also comes up here. It's
really that the way you're standing, the choreography also reflects something of
your כוונה. kavanah. Right, yeah, excellent, correct. Okay, so let's just do
one more section. רבי אליעזר אומר העושה תפילתו קבע אין תפילתו תחנונים.
Rabbi Eliezer omer ha'oseh tfilato keva ein tfilato tachanunim. So רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says if somebody makes their תפילה tfilah fixed, it's not
considered to be supplication. Now what is רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer saying?
Some scholars understand that he actually is rejecting the entire idea of
שמנה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. By preceding רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, you had
an opinion that says all eighteen ברכות, brachos, a version of the,
a מעין, me'ein, a digest. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says if you
know well, all eighteen, if you don't know well, you do a
digest. Comes along רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and says, you know, if
you make your prayer fixed, it doesn't really count as supplication to
God. So some scholars, meaning not the, you know, sort of academics
think that he's rejecting the whole idea of statutory prayer. You should
just say your own stuff. Don't bother with שמנה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei.
It seems very bizarre that that type of a radical opinion would
come in such a sort of cloaked way and that's really what
he is saying. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara understands it
to be. But that's also what Charlie was saying the other day
about Christianity and certain things in prayer that it's, yeah, it only
matters if it's totally, I understand where that could be coming from.
But again, if it meant to express itself in halakhic terms to
say I don't think you דאוון daven a שמנה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei
in an entire פרק perek where everybody is assuming that this fixed
prayer, you assume he would have said it in something that's a
little bit less than an aphorism like this, if he really had
a halakhic position like that to say. So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara understands it to be. מאי קבע? Mai keva? What does
it mean if you make it fixed, it's not good? אמר רבי
יעקב בר אידי אמר רבי אושעיא כל שתפילתו דומה עליו כמשא. Amar
Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi amar Rabbi Oshaya kol she-tfilato domah alav k'masa.
That your prayer is like a burden, ugh, I gotta pray again.
So if you have to approach it in a way of being
seen as an opportunity. Now רב Rav Soloveitchik explained this very beautifully.
He said, he said look, he said normally there's a debate whether
מצוות צריכות כוונה. mitzvot tzrichot kavanah. Do you have to have כוונה
kavanah before you blow the שופר, shofar, I'm about to be יוצא
yotzei the מצות שופר, mitzvat shofar, or you know, before you do
the שמע, Shema, I'm about to be יוצא yotzei the מצות שמע.
mitzvat Shema. He said by שמנה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, the normal כוונה
kavanah we talk about anyway is knowing you're standing before God, knowing
what the words mean. What about the כוונה kavanah of being יוצא
yotzei your obligation of תפילה tfilah according to the רמב״ם Rambam it's
a biblical obligation? Do you need that כוונה? kavanah? So רב Rav
Soloveitchik said not only do you not need that כוונה, kavanah, but
if you have that כוונה, kavanah, you're violating the statement of רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, you're making your תפילה tfilah קבע. keva. you should
be approaching it as an opportunity, not as an obligation. Now, Rabbi
Eliezer probably the גמרא *Gemara* says it a little harsher, you don't
approach it as a burden. You can do something out of an
obligation that's not a burden. But nevertheless, the רב *Rav* takes it
one step further and says you shouldn't even say I'm doing it
because it says in שולחן ערוך *Shulchan Aruch* I have to דאוון
*daven* three times a day. It's true you do have to דאוון
*daven* three times a day, but you should be doing it out
of a sense of an opportunity, out of תחנונים *tachanunim* and not
out of קבע *keva*. Now I have a question as far as
sometimes you don't feel like דאוונינג *davening* and you really feel that
it's a מוסר *mussar*. I understand. And also the issue of עומד
לפני המלך *omed lifnei hamelech* that you wouldn't stand in front of
a מלך בשר ודם *melech basar vedam* in that state of mind.
Right. So we're not saying no, we're not saying that far. We're
saying it's not ideal, but not so far that if that's your
only choice you shouldn't דאוון *daven*. That would be taking it to
the extreme. Let me read a little bit more. Hold on. Okay.
רבנן אמרי *Rabanan amri* כל שאינו אומר בלשון תחנונים *kol she-eino omer
balashon tachanunim*. Now it's not just how you feel, it's whether you
say it בלשון תחנונים *balashon tachanunim*. Now what does it mean to
say... By the way, look at רש״י *Rashi* כמסוי *kemasoy* בלשון קבע
*balashon keva* חוק קבוע הוא עלי לפלל *chok kavua hu alai lifallel*
וצריך אני לצאת ידי חובתי *vetzarich ani latzeit yedei chovasi*. So you
see what the רב *Rav* סולובייצ׳יק *Soloveitchik* said is already in רש״י
*Rashi*. It just says you say I do it because I have
to, I have to be יוצא *yotzei*. Okay. The next opinion is
if you don't say it בלשון תחנונים *balashon tachanunim*. Now does that
mean... what does לשון *lashon* mean? If it's presumably it means more
than just your feeling of obligation, it means how you actually articulate
the words. Are you saying it in a way that's just rote,
or are you saying it in a way that you really are
putting some feeling into what you are saying? רבה ורב יוסף דרמי
תרוייהו *Rabbah veRav Yosef darmi tarvayhu* Rabbah and Rav Yosef both say,
כל שאינו יכול לחדש בו דבר *kol she-eino yachol lechadesh bo davar*.
They say it's not enough what you're thinking, it's not enough of
the emotion in your voice, it's actually also the words you're saying
and that according to Rabbi Eliezer you have to add a personal
text into the fixed text. And if you can't insert a personal
text, then you are making it קבע *keva* and not תחנונים *tachanunim*.
Not to say you're not יוצא *yotzei*, but you're certainly not doing
what is the ideal. אמר רב זירא *Amar Rav Zeira* said רב
זירא *Rav Zeira*, אנא יכילנא לחדושי במילתא *ana yachilna lechidushei bamilsa*. I
could add something new into the text when I דאוון *daven* ומסתפינא
דילמא מיטריפנא *umistafina dilma mitaraivna* exactly evoking the theme from before, I'm
afraid to start adding personal insertions because I'm going to get confused
and I will lose where I'm holding and I'll mess up the
right text. אביי בר אבין ורב חנינא בר אבין דאמרי תרוייהו *Abaye
bar Avin veRav Chanina bar Avin damri tarvayhu* they both say, כל
שאינו מתפלל עם דמומי חמה *kol she-eino mitpallel im dimumey chama*. Here's
a very nice idea. Maybe it's not what you're thinking or feeling
and maybe it's not your text, maybe it's your circumstances, your environment.
How much does your environment make you connect to the words of
the prayer? So if you're דאוונינג *davening* it with the rising and
the setting of the sun, and that's a very different way about
thinking about שחרית *Shachris* and מנחה *Mincha* and whatever, it's not קרבנות
*korbanos*, it's connecting to nature and the rising and the setting of
the sun, then that creates a sense of תחנונים *tachanunim* putting you
in touch with God and nature as opposed to just a fixed
text being done in a vacuum. So דאמרי רבי חייא בר אבין
אמר רבי יוחנן *de-amri Rabbi Chiya bar Abin amar Rabbi Yochanan* מצוה
להתפלל עם דמומי חמה *mitzvah lehitpallel im dimumey chama*. It's a מצוה
*mitzvah* to do it with the reddening of the sun, the shining
of the sun. ואמר רב זירא מאי קרא *Ve-amar Rav Zeira mai
krah* ייראוך עם שמש ולפני ירח דור דורים *yira'ucha im shamesh velifnei
yareiach dor dorim*. So you see it with the sun and therefore
to say the שמונה עשרה *Shemoneh Esrei* with the sun, this is
the idea of ותיקין *vatikin*. I would just add at the end,
לייט אביי במערבא *leti'at liba bema'arava* אמאן דמצלי עם דמומי חמה *amandei
matzi dimumey chama* in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* they would curse or
mock somebody that would try to דאוון *daven* exactly at sunrise. מאי
טעמא *Mai ta'ama* דילמא מיטרפא ליה שעתא *Dilma mitarfi lei sha'ata* because
you'll similarly evoke the same idea, you'll get confused. You'll be so
focused on doing it with the sunrise you'll miss the right time
for שמונה עשרה *Shemoneh Esrei*. So beautifully encapsulated in this גמרא *Gemara*,
I gotta tell you these couple lines that we went a little
faster than we should have are so beautiful because they are a
real distillation of the tension of fixed prayer with personal prayer, that
the idea we want to have the personal prayer, how do you
do it? Do you keep the fixed text and it's a question
about thoughts, feelings, emotions, do you actually change the text? At what
stage are we afraid that if we allow you too much latitude
in terms of your personal insertion, are you going to undermine the
fixed nature of the text? Are you going to be מטריד *matrid*
distracted and actually do the actual ritual incorrectly, do the fixed text
incorrectly? How much can we allow this balance and dialectic to play
out? But here is exactly גמרא *Gemara* not saying you don't do
the fixed text, but how do you bring those two experiences together?
And it nicely also parallels that in the middle of discussing fixed
שמונה עשרה *Shemoneh Esrei* we inserted the private prayer of רבי נחוניא
בן הקנה *Rabbi Nechunya ben HaKanah*. So here again in the שמונה
עשרה *Shemoneh Esrei* we're talking about how do you make that also
a personal type of a prayer and different ways in which that
tension can play itself out.